So if you have heard of Gemini CLI, it
basically is an AI agent that completely
transforms your terminal experience. So
if you're a developer, you don't need to
switch context when you're working on a
project. Now, most recently, Gemini CLI
got updated and they have introduced a
new experimental feature called agent
skills. In this video, I want to talk
about what Gemini CLI agent skills are.
How can one get that activated within
Gemini CLI and how can you build your
own agent pretty quickly? So, I'm on
their documentation site where they
clearly define what agent skills are. We
will go through together how to activate
this. So, don't worry about it. But you
can clearly see here that agent skills
allow you to extend Gemini CLI with
specialized expertise. And this is built
on the open standard from Enthropic
which is the agent skills. Right now,
one of the coolest thing I love about
this is once you have created a skill,
Gemini can autonomously decide when to
employ that skill based on your request
and the skills description. I think this
is pretty cool. Once once you've
developed like multiple skills, Gemini
is going to get many more superpowers,
right? So, what we will do now is we
will actually get into the terminal and
we will build a skill right from the
scratch so that you can get to see how
easy and how quick it is to build these
kind of skills. All right. So with that
let's get into our terminal. So because
agent skill is an experimental feature
it must be enabled in the settings and
it's not directly available in the
default mainstable release right. So to
use agent skills like you're going to do
this install with the CLI preview. So
I'm going to give this command and it's
going to run this pretty quickly and
once it is done then we are going to
invoke a Gemini using the Gemini
command. All right. So we'll give it a
second for it to complete. All right. So
it has completed the install. So now
let's write Gemini. Now just typing
Gemini will invoke the Gemini CLI. So
we're going to get into that pretty
quickly and then I will show you how to
get to skills. Right. So there you go.
We have Gemini. So what you need to do
is you need to type settings and this is
where you will see that by default the
preview models or the preview features
over here is disabled. So what we're
going to do is we're just going to press
enter. And now you can see that it has
enabled. Right now once you're done with
this and you can also see what other
things you want to change here. Enable
prompt completion. You can do that.
There are a lot of interesting things
that you might want to change here.
Right? So the format of the output is
text or JSON. I would like to keep it as
text. Maybe you want to hide the window
title and stuff like that. So this is
something pretty cool. If you want to
just work on this and make your stuff
more interesting, you're welcome to do
that. Right now once you're done with
this, then you press R. And that way you
know you're going to exit from this and
it is going to apply all the changes.
Right? So I'm now outside of this. And
now when I go to settings again I should
be able to find skills.
You see there. So now I can see agent
skills. And now I'm going to press this
to enable it. So first you need to
enable the preview features and then you
need to come back in settings and then
you need to enable the agent skills as
well and then you press R again and then
you will come out and that will apply
the changes. So as soon as you're done
with that your agent skills are now
enabled right fastest way to check this
is going to be just type skills and you
will start seeing the command which goes
along with skills. So you can just say
that okay list all the skills that are
available and now you're seeing that
there is zero skill available because we
have not created any. Okay. So as next
step now that we have enabled the skills
we are going to create a couple of
skills and see for ourselves you know
how they are. All right. So let's get
into it. All right. So creation of skill
is actually pretty simple. All it
requires is a basic structure like this
within a skills.mmd file which will be
within the root directory. And usually
it is placed within dogemini skills
folder right which we will see very
quickly. And this is a basic structure
right. So you name the skill, you give
it a description and then you basically
provide some instructions. So for
example, this is a example that has been
given. The name of the skill is code
reviewer. This is a description and this
is the prompt or the instruction that is
being given to uh Gemini. Right? So this
becomes a skill. Now for my example,
what I'm going to do is I want to get a
tech review news aggregated based on the
URL that I'm giving to Gemini, right? So
I want it to to develop that kind of a
skill within Gemini CLI. it can come and
say that hey give me all the techreated
news from wire.com right and then I
don't need to code anything I don't need
to tell it anything else it'll go to
that website scrape everything and come
back with a response right so that will
be a skill which is reusable so that's
what we're going to do okay so keeping
that in mind what we will do is we will
go into Gemini um sorry we will go into
cloud shell and here you see I've
already created that skill and this is
the skill.md file and that the structure
that I have followed is exactly similar
to what we discussed right so I've given
it a name fetches and summarizes the
latest tech news related to a specific
website it will ask the user for a URL
and then please provide the URL and then
once the user provides the URL it will
go figure out using the web fetch tool
and come back with some main news right
so this is a skill that that I've used
right so now that I've done this now
what I'm going to do is I'm going to go
back to Gemini and I'm going to type
Gemini again oops I'm going to type
Gemini again and then first of all we'll
activate the skill and then we we'll see
the skill in action. Okay. All right. So
now we are in Gemini CLI and in order to
activate the skill all you need to do is
send a command like this activate skill
and name of the skill that you already
have and it says that hey you're about
to enable this specialized skill. This
is what it's going to do. I'm going to
say okay go ahead and do it. And this is
the beauty of agentic AI within your
terminal right it is doing this. So now
you know it's activated and it's asking
me exactly what we had thought right? So
I'm just going to take the wire.com and
then I'm just going to say okay go ahead
and do this for me. So now it is going
to do the fetch and it's looking into
the instructions as we had as part of
the skill right and then it is
constructing an answer for us right so
it's already also telling us what it is
doing and there you go it's very fast
I've summarized the main tech news
articles so you can see that it is like
absolutely latest right so let's go to
the website right now and see what is
happening and there you go all of the
things that that you are seeing over
here right so if you go back to your CLI
you you're seeing all of those things
which are mentioned over here right so
this was it. We just created a quick
skill for us and we used it right within
the Gemini CLI and I believe this is
going to explode and this is going to
become very powerful. One last thing
that I wanted to show you guys was how
Gemini CLI skills are going to be
available and are available already in
Gemini CLI extensions. So for example, I
think I saw something which is really
cool. For example, this is skill portter
which basically converts all the cloud
skills to Gemini skill extensions and
vice versa which is pretty fascinating
right so I believe this is how you know
you're going to be able to potentially
monetize I don't know probably right if
you are able to create some very
interesting skill which can be used
across the board because remember skills
is more of a protocol right which is
going to be used across the board
anthropic claude obviously has skills
and now Gemini CLI has skills as an
experimentation I'm hoping that it
becomes part of Right. So I think it's a
good idea for all of us to be aware of
these things and learn as much as we can
and this would definitely be part of the
overall agentic AI ecosystem. All right.
So that is what I wanted to show you
guys today. I hope you enjoyed the
video. If you have any questions, please
do let me know in the comment section.
And if you found any value in this
video, please do hit that like button
and please do subscribe and also share
it with your friends. I'll highly
appreciate it. Thank you very much for
your time. I will see you in the next
one.